Hi guys, I'm Prevna and welcome back.
This is part 2 of the Back to Basics series.
In case you don't know about this series,
some time ago, I started a brand new series on this channel called Back to Basics.
The idea behind this series is to share some simple styling and grooming tips
that anyone can easily inculcate in their routine without having to be a fashionista.
So in part 1, I shared some grooming tips with you.
What am I going to do today?
Today, I'm going to share with you how I drape a saree.
The irony is that on this channel, I've made a lot of styling videos
but I didn't make a single video sharing how I drape the saree.
So this is the video that you all had been asking for.
I hope after this video, every girl who seems to be very complicated in her draping
will get all this uncomplicated and she embraces the gorgeous saree.
I hope you enjoy this video. Let's get started.
Let's talk about the blouse first because I'm going to drape both the sarees with this.
The fabric is mesh and the lining inside is a sweetheart neckline style
which I think looks so pretty.
The back is cut deep and there are hooks on the collar and side.
Now, if you're wondering where I bought this blouse from,
I actually got it stitched 6 years back and wore it to my college convocation ceremony as well.
Now for the underskirt, I'm wearing a traditional petticoat.
One important tip that I want to share is that petticoat is the base of all the draping
and it will hang on to your saree.
So, if this guy is loose, you are in trouble. So, tie the petticoat tight.
Don't stop the blood circulation but it should be tight.
And as long as the petticoat is tight, your saree will not go anywhere.
Now, let's come to the actual topic.
I'll say it in the YouTube comments. So, this is the point where the video starts.
Okay.
Start with grabbing one end of the saree.
This is the non-fancy end which will go inside.
You have to place it on the center and start moving from your left.
Bring it around once and tuck it to your right.
While doing this step, ensure that the length of the saree is as long as it should not touch the floor.
As in, it should not touch the floor as the saree should not touch the floor.
But at the same time, it should be so long that if someone is looking at you from the back,
then only show your heels.
This determines how graceful your look is.
And this is precisely the reason why everyone suggests that you should wear heels before the saree drips
because you will end up messing the length later.
So, once you are done with this step, next you have to grab the fancier end which is the pallu of the saree.
And bring it around from your left to the right and place it on your left shoulder.
This is the point where you will decide how long the pallu should be.
Now, this is again a very critical step as critical as the length of the saree.
So, I like the length of the pallu from the bottom.
It should fall on my calf area.
If I tell you precisely, it should be 2 inches longer than the knee, like that is the length I like.
And I have personally observed that if the pallu is long, then the all over look looks more graceful.
Also, the height also looks more graceful.
So, this is again very important.
Once you have decided the length of the pallu,
after that, you have to grab the top part of the pallu tightly from the back to the left leg.
And you have to tuck it on the left side.
Now, at this point, some people put a pin here in the downward slanting motion.
And I have seen a lot of people and YouTubers do it.
But this trick never worked for me.
So, I will show you what I do.
So, first of all, we will make pleats.
Whose pleats will we make?
The pleats of the fabric that you can see in the front.
To make pleats, grab the fabric from the right hand like this.
Keep the index finger in front of you, keep the thumb behind you.
The middle finger will support the index finger in front of you.
And the pinky finger will support the thumb.
I know at this point, you all must be like,
what is this?
This must be freaking you out.
And I used to feel the same when I used to see my mom dress up.
But, I mean, once you do it, believe me, it's not that complex.
Now, it's time to make the first pleat.
So, to make the first pleat, you will place your fingers like this.
And then, you will place it in front of your belly button like this.
Why?
Because here, you will check that when you are placing the first pleat in front of your belly button,
whether it is a straight line or not.
If it is not, then add a little fabric in it.
And keep doing it until there is a straight line in front of you.
Once your straight line is formed, this is the point where the first pleat will be yours.
So, once you have that point in front of you,
hold it with your index finger and middle finger in front of you,
adjust it with your thumb.
On the right side, you will feel that there is a lot of extra fabric left.
Don't worry, no one is going to see it.
First, you have to make the pleats perfect.
And after that, you will make the second pleat by rotating your fingers in the same way.
Here, there is another important point.
To make the second pleat a little smaller than the first pleat,
it cleanses the pleats and pleats look better.
Once you have made the second pleat, you do it like this.
Third, fourth, fifth, you will make all the pleats of the same size as the second.
The first should be bigger than the second, third, fourth, fifth.
All the pleats will be of the same size and length.
The first will be a little bigger.
Once your pleats are made, gather them all and clean up each pleat.
At this point, you can also apply some pins on the pleats.
Just in case, if any pleat is opened, then it is not like that.
Once the pleats are opened, you can do it.
I am so used to skipping this point.
And then, looking at the length from the bottom,
according to the height, you have to tuck the pleats inside.
Now, on the right side, there is a little bit of fabric left.
Don't worry about this.
Tuck it in cleanly.
It will hide under the pleats.
I don't want to show this area.
Tuck it in.
Clean up the left side that you want to show.
You have to make this part a little tighter,
so that the shape of the body is enhanced.
You know that shape, the curve from the waist to the hips.
This is the point where we enhance that curve.
Tighten it a little.
Push the extra fabric under the pleats.
And then, with the safety pin,
pin the extra fabric along with the pleats.
Now, the last and final step.
That is adjusting the pleats.
Pin it properly to the length you had decided to pin there.
And keep in mind that pinning from the back of the shoulder
gives a little cleaner look.
If you are reaching with your hand, then do it yourself.
Call your mom, sister, brother, husband, whatever is available,
pin it from the back and you are done.
Now, because this sari is lightweight,
making the pleats was a little easy and you didn't have to adjust anything.
But, if you are wearing a silk sari,
then this step is not that easy.
So, what I did is that I also draped a silk sari
just to make it easier for you all.
So, largely everything is the same.
Just two steps are different.
First of all, when you are making pleats,
then there are chances that the pleats don't look clean.
Everything will look fine from the top, but the bottom will be messed up.
So, what you can do is call for help, husband, brother, mom,
whatever is available at home, call them.
Like I called Mr. Husband here.
And I asked him to sit there and from the bottom,
ask them to get us the plate.
The line that is coming from the top,
while following it,
align the pleats with each other.
And once this step is done,
then you can run a little warm iron on your pleats.
And the pleats will be completely set.
Another thing that I like to do with the heavy sari,
which is a little heavy,
is that I gently tuck the pleats in
from the safety pin so that they get a clean look.
So, what I do for this is that the bottom part of the pleats
that is coming from the front,
I neatly pleat it like this.
And on the left side, I pin it towards the top.
What happens with this is that,
while eating or talking,
if the left hand gets a little lower,
then it won't be like the whole pleat is open
and falling on the ground.
It looks a little clean and all over,
it becomes easy to handle the pleats for you.
So, this is how I drape a sari.
A lot of you guys wanted to see it.
So, here is the tutorial for it.
I hope you got some tips and tricks.
And by following this video,
you can easily drape the sari.
That is my motive behind this video.
If you liked it, of course, give it a thumbs up.
Thank you for watching this video.
Take care and bye.